<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0"
	xml:lang="en-US"
	>
	<title type="text">Natural England</title>
	<subtitle type="text">News and updates from Natural England</subtitle>

	<updated>2026-07-23T08:35:59Z</updated>

	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" />
	<id>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/feed/</id>
	<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/feed/" />

	
<icon>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2024/11/cropped-Natural-England-green_no-line-32x32.png</icon>
	<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Marian Spain</name>
					</author>

		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Where nature strengthens community: celebrating England&#039;s first accredited Nature Towns]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/23/where-nature-strengthens-community-celebrating-englands-first-accredited-nature-towns/" />

		<id>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/?p=7464</id>
		<updated>2026-07-23T08:35:59Z</updated>
		<published>2026-07-23T08:35:31Z</published>
		<category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Connecting People with Nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Development" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Green Infrastructure" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Growth" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Mental health and wellbeing" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Natural England" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="development" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="green infrastructure" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="health and wellbeing" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="nature towns" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="nature towns and cities" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="urban greening" />
		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Marian Spain, Chief Executive, Natural England In this blog, NE Chief Executive Marian Spain reflects on her visit to Bournemouth, Christchurch and Poole (BCP), alongside senior leaders from The National Lottery Heritage Fund and the National Trust, to see …]]></summary>

					<content type="html" xml:base="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/23/where-nature-strengthens-community-celebrating-englands-first-accredited-nature-towns/"><![CDATA[
<p><em><strong>By Marian Spain, Chief Executive, Natural England</strong></em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><em>In this blog, NE Chief Executive Marian Spain reflects on her visit to Bournemouth, Christchurch and Poole (BCP), alongside senior leaders from The National Lottery Heritage Fund and the National Trust, to see firsthand the amazing benefits of the Nature Towns and Cities programme.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><a id="_msocom_1"></a>What makes a great place to live? Increasingly, the answer includes easy access to nature. In Bournemouth, Christchurch and Poole (BCP), residents benefit from an extensive network of parks, green spaces and coastal habitats; spaces that support health, wellbeing and community life, and help people connect with nature close to home.</p>



<p>But what does it really take to make that happen at scale, and to sustain it? That was the question in my mind this week when I joined Eilish McGuinness, Chief Executive of the National Lottery Heritage Fund, and Hilary McGrady, Director General of the National Trust, the founding partners of Nature Towns and Cities to visit BCP Council and see firsthand what becomes possible when local ambition meets national partnership.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="620" height="465" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Photo-20-07-2026-13-47-14-620x465.jpg" alt="Photo showing 4 smiling women in smart casual clothing standing in a row looking at the camera, in a field with the coastline in the background." class="wp-image-7467" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Photo-20-07-2026-13-47-14-620x465.jpg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Photo-20-07-2026-13-47-14-310x233.jpg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Photo-20-07-2026-13-47-14-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Photo-20-07-2026-13-47-14-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>Left to right: Eilish McGuinness, CEO of The National Lottery Heritage Fund, Cllr Millie Earl, Leader of BCP Council, Hilary McGrady, Director General at National Trust and Marian Spain CEO Natural England at Hengitsbury Head, Nature Reserve, Dorset. © BCP Council</em></figcaption></figure>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A national leader for urban nature</strong></h4>



<p>In 2025, BCP became the first place to receive official Nature Towns accreditation. This recognition reflects more than a decade of work embedding nature into planning, public health, climate resilience, and community life, with results to show for it. It goes far beyond planting trees or maintaining parks.</p>



<p>Since 2023, BCP Council and its local partners have gone further still, helping to shape the Nature Towns and Cities programme at a national level, acting as pioneer and mentor to urban areas across the country.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Transforming parks and communities</strong></h4>



<p>Across a population of 409,000, BCP and its partners are delivering an ambitious green transformation. The council is upgrading fourteen urban parks into multi-functional community hubs, blending nature-friendly planting with community cafes and volunteering opportunities. The BCP Nature Pledge empowers residents, businesses, and schools to turn their own outdoor spaces into wildlife havens. And major landscape-scale projects including the Stour Valley Park and Littletown Greenway now connect fragmented green corridors across the area.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="620" height="324" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/NT-images-James-Dobson-Redhill-Park-Bournemouth-1-620x324.jpeg" alt="Photograph of two people working in an allotment on a rainy day, overlayed with the Nature Towns and Cities logo and graphics of flowers and swirls in green and orange." class="wp-image-7475" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/NT-images-James-Dobson-Redhill-Park-Bournemouth-1-620x324.jpeg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/NT-images-James-Dobson-Redhill-Park-Bournemouth-1-310x162.jpeg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/NT-images-James-Dobson-Redhill-Park-Bournemouth-1.jpeg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>Picture of Redhill Park Bournemouth © James Dobson, National Trust Images</em></figcaption></figure>



<p>Each of BCP's parks and green spaces generates around £20 of health and wellbeing value per visit, underlining the economic as well as social case for this investment.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Nature as preventative infrastructure</strong></h4>



<p>BCP faces real challenges. The area has significant health and social inequalities, including a nine-year gap in male life expectancy between its most and least deprived communities. Access to green space is uneven, with canopy cover lowest in some of the borough's most disadvantaged neighbourhoods.</p>



<p>The council increasingly views nature not as an amenity but as preventative infrastructure, something that supports physical and mental health, reduces inequalities, and strengthens community resilience. Targeted investment in areas like West Howe and Kinson deliberately prioritises those who have historically had least access to quality green space.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>A model for towns and cities everywhere</strong></h4>



<p>As one of England's most densely populated urban areas, BCP's success in embedding nature into a constrained urban environment carries a powerful message for towns and cities facing similar pressures around growth, climate resilience, and public health. The question BCP has answered, not just in strategy documents but on the ground, is whether genuinely nature-rich urban places are achievable at scale. The answer is clearly yes.</p>



<p>Urban areas across the country are now taking the approaches pioneered here and adapting them to their own contexts, demonstrating that a greener, healthier, and more resilient urban future is within reach, wherever you are.</p>



<p>Eilish McGuinness, Chief Executive, The National Lottery Heritage Fund, said:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>"It was fantastic to discover how closely council leaders, local charities, volunteers and community champions are working together to reimagine the role of nature in people’s everyday lives. BCP are creating a Nature Towns and Cities partnership model that will lead by example UK-wide, showing how investing in green spaces can strengthen local pride, improve natural heritage and biodiversity and drive economic growth.&nbsp;It’s thanks to players of the National Lottery that the Heritage Fund can spearhead funding to support urban communities in their drive to save our precious natural heritage for all to enjoy."</p>
</blockquote>



<p>What BCP has pioneered, towns and cities across the country are now making their own. The model is scalable, the benefits are real, and the ambition is national. Over the next decade, Nature Towns and Cities will work with one hundred urban areas across the UK so that many more communities can enjoy the healthier, greener, more resilient places they deserve.</p>



<p>Visit the website to find out more: <a href="https://naturetownsandcities.org.uk/">Home - Nature Towns and Cities</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="620" height="467" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/NTC_Core-logo_GreenGrey_RGB.pdf-620x467.jpg" alt="Nature Towns and Cities logo - black text and green butterfly graphic against a white background." class="wp-image-7471" style="aspect-ratio:1.3276756247053276;width:99px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/NTC_Core-logo_GreenGrey_RGB.pdf-620x467.jpg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/NTC_Core-logo_GreenGrey_RGB.pdf-310x233.jpg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/NTC_Core-logo_GreenGrey_RGB.pdf-1536x1156.jpg 1536w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/NTC_Core-logo_GreenGrey_RGB.pdf.jpg 1845w" sizes="(max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content>
		
					<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/23/where-nature-strengthens-community-celebrating-englands-first-accredited-nature-towns/#comments" thr:count="0" />
			<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/23/where-nature-strengthens-community-celebrating-englands-first-accredited-nature-towns/feed/" thr:count="0" />
			<thr:total>0</thr:total>
			</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Matthew Heard</name>
					</author>

		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Natural England publishes Hen Harrier Brood Management Trial]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/22/natural-england-publishes-hen-harrier-brood-management-trial/" />

		<id>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/?p=7459</id>
		<updated>2026-07-22T12:44:19Z</updated>
		<published>2026-07-22T12:45:00Z</published>
		<category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Birds" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Evidence" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Hen Harriers" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Licensing" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Monitoring" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Natural England" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="birds of prey" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="brood management" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Brood Management Trial" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="hen harrier" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="wildlife crime" />
		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Matthew Heard, National Delivery Director, Natural England Hen Harriers are one of the UK’s rarest birds of prey. However, they are at the centre of a long-running conflict because they prey on red grouse, which are managed for grouse …]]></summary>

					<content type="html" xml:base="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/22/natural-england-publishes-hen-harrier-brood-management-trial/"><![CDATA[
<p><em><strong>By Matthew Heard, National Delivery Director, Natural England</strong></em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><em>Hen Harriers are one of the UK’s rarest birds of prey. However, they are at the centre of a long-running conflict because they prey on red grouse, which are managed for grouse shooting. To help address this problem, Natural England and its partners have explored approaches that could support both Hen Harrier conservation and sustainable grouse shooting. This blog explains the results of the 'brood management' trial, which concluded that this activity contributed to increased numbers of nesting Hen Harriers on some grouse moors, and presents the full evaluation report which has now been published</em>.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p>Hen Harriers are iconic birds of upland landscapes, yet they remain at the centre of one of England’s most intractable human–wildlife conflicts. Despite being protected by law, they are illegally killed because they are predators of red grouse, and law enforcement alone has not been successful in improving their numbers. Therefore, we have been working with our partners to explore ways of reducing the impact of Hen Harriers on grouse shoots, to support thriving Hen Harrier populations that coexist with sustainable grouse shooting. One method, known as 'brood management', has been trialed in recent years as an avenue to improving tolerance of Hen Harriers on grouse moors.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="484" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/AikCx-7A-620x484.jpeg" alt="Hen Harrier in flight against a brown grass backdrop." class="wp-image-7458" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/AikCx-7A-620x484.jpeg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/AikCx-7A-310x242.jpeg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/AikCx-7A.jpeg 1200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>Hen Harrier. © Natural England</em></figcaption></figure>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>What is Brood Management? </strong> </h4>



<p>Brood management reduces Hen Harrier nest density on grouse moors by temporarily removing the eggs and/or broods of chicks under licence, rearing them in captivity, and releasing the young birds back into the wild at a suitable location, once they are able to fly and disperse. Providing a lawful way to reduce predation of nesting Hen Harriers on grouse promotes coexistence between grouse moor interests and Hen Harriers. </p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>The Brood Management Trial – recap of the evidence gathered</strong> </h4>



<p>Brood management was trialed under licence in northern England between 2018 and 2024, through a partnership of Natural England, the Moorland Association, the International Centre for Birds of Prey, the Game &amp; Wildlife Conservation Trust and the Hawk &amp; Owl Trust.</p>



<p>The final reports of the trial have now been <a href="https://publications.naturalengland.org.uk/publication/4676200008777728" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">published</a>.   </p>



<p><a href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2025/04/14/conclusion-of-hen-harrier-brood-management-trial/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Headline results were published in 2025:</a> </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>During the trial, Hen Harrier numbers increased substantially in areas managed for grouse shooting where brood management was available (but not in other areas).</li>



<li>Illegal killing continued throughout the trial, but no crime hotspots were identified within brood management areas.</li>



<li>Although the act of safely rearing a small number of chicks in captivity probably made a small contribution to population growth, the numbers involved were too low to explain the increase in nesting pairs that took place over this period. <a href="https://www.bto.org/our-work/science/publications/reports/bto-research-reports/00778-hen-harrier-population-modelling-england" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Research by the British Trust for Ornithology</a> suggests the increase was more likely driven by higher survival rates and greater settlement and breeding by wild birds. </li>



<li>At the end of the trial, Natural England and its independent Natural England Science Advisory Committee (NESAC) concluded that the availability of brood management had probably contributed to population growth, primarily through reduced nest disturbance and improved settlement on some grouse moors.</li>



<li>NESAC advised that the widespread use and awareness of satellite tagging and monitoring as part of the trial likely contributed to reduced disturbance and improved breeding success. Importantly, the effects of the availability of brood management could not be fully separated from those of the accompanying tagging and monitoring programme.</li>
</ul>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="827" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/IMG_0188-002-620x827.jpg" alt="Close up shot of a hen harrier chick 's head and neck in profile against a blurred grassy background." class="wp-image-7457" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/IMG_0188-002-620x827.jpg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/IMG_0188-002-310x413.jpg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/IMG_0188-002-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/IMG_0188-002-1536x2048.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>Brood managed hen harrier chick. © Natural England</em></figcaption></figure>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Review of the evidence for brood management</strong> </h4>



<p>Natural England recognises that brood management is controversial. Concerns include whether brood management addresses the underlying drivers of illegal killing, whether it distracts from the need for effective law enforcement, and whether increases in Hen Harrier numbers are really due to brood management rather than increased monitoring and satellite tagging. </p>



<p>Having carefully considered the available evidence and advice, Natural England's view is that the availability of brood management, including satellite tagging, monitoring and communication of bird locations likely contributed to improved breeding success in some areas. </p>



<p>Current evidence supports use of brood management under licence where projects follow the methods used in the trial. This is likely to include satellite tagging and monitoring, subject to case-by-case assessment. Such projects should be for the explicit aim of increasing Hen Harrier numbers by reducing illegal killing and disturbance. </p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Not a substitute for tackling wildlife crime </strong> </h4>



<p>More widely, brood management can be justified as a Hen Harrier conservation tool when used alongside diversionary feeding, engagement, enforcement, monitoring and research. It is not a substitute for directly tackling wildlife crime. </p>



<p>These views are based on the currently available evidence, including the results of the Brood Management Trial, and will be kept under review as new evidence emerges. </p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Acknowledgements and Further Reading</strong> </h4>



<p>Natural England would like to thank all the project partners who worked together on making the trial and evaluation possible, as well as the landowners who allowed access for release and monitoring. </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>The final reports from the Hen Harrier Brood Management Trial have now been published <a href="https://publications.naturalengland.org.uk/publication/4676200008777728" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.  </li>



<li>Hen Harrier Brood Management Trial Evaluation: The effectiveness of brood management as a mechanism for supporting Hen Harrier recovery.  <a href="https://publications.naturalengland.org.uk/publication/6614553511854080" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Natural England Research Report NERR153</a> </li>



<li>Hen Harrier Brood Management Trial: Interim social science evaluation. <a href="https://publications.naturalengland.org.uk/publication/6299981114507264" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Natural England Research Report NERR160</a> </li>



<li>Hen Harrier Brood Management Trial: Findings from the social science survey of moorland managers Authors: National Centre for Social Research. <a href="https://publications.naturalengland.org.uk/publication/6497589393096704" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Natural England Commission Report NECR615</a> </li>
</ul>
]]></content>
		
					<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/22/natural-england-publishes-hen-harrier-brood-management-trial/#comments" thr:count="0" />
			<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/22/natural-england-publishes-hen-harrier-brood-management-trial/feed/" thr:count="0" />
			<thr:total>0</thr:total>
			</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Natural England</name>
					</author>

		<title type="html"><![CDATA[High Court judgment threatens protections for England’s internationally important wildlife sites]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/17/high-court-judgment-threatens-protections-for-englands-internationally-important-wildlife-sites/" />

		<id>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/?p=7454</id>
		<updated>2026-07-17T16:10:16Z</updated>
		<published>2026-07-17T16:09:58Z</published>
		<category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Licensing" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Natural England" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Special Protection Area" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Wildlife" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Gamebird Licensing" />
		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[Natural England intends to appeal a High Court judgment arising from a judicial review brought by the British Association for Shooting and Conservation (BASC) concerning gamebird release licensing. Gamebird release licensing was introduced in 2021 to protect internationally important species …]]></summary>

					<content type="html" xml:base="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/17/high-court-judgment-threatens-protections-for-englands-internationally-important-wildlife-sites/"><![CDATA[
<p>Natural England intends to appeal a High Court judgment arising from a judicial review brought by the British Association for Shooting and Conservation (BASC) concerning gamebird release licensing.</p>



<p>Gamebird release licensing was introduced in 2021 to protect internationally important species and habitats found within Special Protection Areas (SPAs) and Special Areas of Conservation (SACs), collectively known as European Sites. A licence is required only where pheasants or red-legged partridges are released on, or within 500 metres of, one of these designated sites. Fewer than 1% of shoots in England are affected.</p>



<p>In recent years, Natural England has taken additional steps through the licensing regime to protect SPA bird populations from the risks posed by bird flu. The disease has caused unprecedented mortality in wild birds worldwide and poses a potentially catastrophic threat to the rare and internationally important species for which many SPAs are designated.</p>



<p>Since the emergence of bird flu, we have carefully considered the risks posed by the disease to protected species and habitats. Throughout this period, we have sought to minimise impacts on gamebird shoots and businesses while continuing to meet our obligations under the Habitats Regulations and wider conservation legislation.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">The legal challenge</h4>



<p>In September 2025, BASC brought a judicial review claim against Natural England.</p>



<p>The claim challenged licence conditions that restricted the keeping of gamebirds in release pens within SPAs and their 500m buffer zones before the beginning of the shooting season. Natural England imposed those conditions to reduce the risk of bird flu transmission from gamebirds, particularly pheasants, to protected wild bird populations. Natural England’s approach sought to minimise that risk by delaying releases until after breeding birds were expected largely to have left SPAs.</p>



<p>BASC argued that Natural England had used its licensing powers for a purpose not authorised by the relevant legislation and had incorrectly interpreted what constitutes a “release into the wild” under section 14 of the Wildlife and Countryside Act 1981. BASC also challenged Natural England’s guidance that a licence would be required where a release pen falls partly within and partly outside a controlled zone.</p>



<p>Natural England’s position was that the conditions were imposed for the purpose Parliament intended: protecting vulnerable species and ensuring compliance with wildlife conservation law. We argued that there is a direct connection between keeping gamebirds in release pens and the licensed activity of releasing them into the wild, because the former activity is undertaken to facilitate the latter.</p>



<p>The case was heard on 1 and 2 July 2026.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">The Court’s decision</h4>



<p>The Court found that Natural England acted beyond its powers in imposing conditions that prevented the keeping of pheasants and partridges within pens in SPAs and their 500m buffer zones before the start of the shooting season. However, BASC’s challenge to Natural England’s guidance on release pens that straddle the boundaries of SPAs and their 500m buffer zones was rejected.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Why we are appealing</h4>



<p>Natural England respectfully disagrees with the judgment and intends to appeal the decision on a number of points of law.</p>



<p>Protecting England’s internationally important wildlife sites and the species they support remains at the heart of our work, and we will continue to use every appropriate legal mechanism available to fulfil that responsibility.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content>
		
					<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/17/high-court-judgment-threatens-protections-for-englands-internationally-important-wildlife-sites/#comments" thr:count="0" />
			<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/17/high-court-judgment-threatens-protections-for-englands-internationally-important-wildlife-sites/feed/" thr:count="0" />
			<thr:total>0</thr:total>
			</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Karyn Haw</name>
					</author>

		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Sherwood Forest’s Major Oak: An ending and a beginning]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/14/sherwood-forests-major-oak-an-ending-and-a-beginning/" />

		<id>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/?p=7448</id>
		<updated>2026-07-14T07:00:26Z</updated>
		<published>2026-07-14T07:00:26Z</published>
		<category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Connecting People with Nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Landscapes" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Natural England" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Woodland" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Ancient oak" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="biodiversity" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Habitat" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Major Oak" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Sherwood Forest" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="tree" />
		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[Karyn Haw, Senior Officer - Nature Recovery Network, East Midlands Area Team Karyn Haw, Senior Officer in Natural England's East Midlands Area Team, reflects on the recent news that Sherwood Forest's iconic Major Oak has died. Drawing on a career …]]></summary>

					<content type="html" xml:base="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/14/sherwood-forests-major-oak-an-ending-and-a-beginning/"><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Karyn Haw, Senior Officer - Nature Recovery Network, East Midlands Area Team</strong></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><em>Karyn Haw, Senior Officer in Natural England's East Midlands Area Team, reflects on the recent news that Sherwood Forest's iconic Major Oak has died. Drawing on a career spent working in the forest, she explores what made this ancient tree so remarkable and the pressures that led to its decline. But this is not simply a story of loss, Karyn also looks ahead to the vital role the Major Oak will continue to play as a rare and irreplaceable habitat, and a lasting symbol of our relationship with the natural world.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p>Last week, I found myself unexpectedly emotional at my desk as news emerged from the Royal Society for the Protection of Birds (RSPB) that the Major Oak has now died. Having spent my entire career working in Sherwood Forest, my connection to its ancient trees is both professional and deeply personal.</p>



<p>These trees are of immense ecological value, but what has always struck me most is the sense of continuity they embody. Ancient oaks like the Major Oak have stood for centuries, quietly witnessing the evolution of the landscape and our relationship with it. They remind us of both the brevity of human timescales and the responsibility we share as temporary custodians of these remarkable ecosystems.</p>



<p>The Major Oak, in particular, holds exceptional significance. Estimated to be over 1,000 years old, it stands at the centre of what was once a royal hunting forest, frequented by English monarchs across the centuries. It is part of the Birklands and Bilhaugh Site of Special Scientific Interest (SSSI) and a Special Area of Conservation (SAC), reflecting its importance at both national and European levels. Ecologically, it has supported an extraordinary diversity of species. Culturally, it has provided a powerful and enduring link between people and nature.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="467" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Major-Oak-Summer-2025.-Credit-Karyn-Haw-620x467.jpg" alt="Major Oak Summer 2025. Credit: Karyn Haw" class="wp-image-7451" style="width:630px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Major-Oak-Summer-2025.-Credit-Karyn-Haw-620x467.jpg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Major-Oak-Summer-2025.-Credit-Karyn-Haw-310x233.jpg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Major-Oak-Summer-2025.-Credit-Karyn-Haw-1536x1157.jpg 1536w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Major-Oak-Summer-2025.-Credit-Karyn-Haw-2048x1542.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Major Oak Summer 2025. Credit: Karyn Haw</figcaption></figure>



<p>However, the same qualities that made the Major Oak so iconic also contributed to its decline. Its popularity, particularly from the Victorian era onwards, brought increasing visitor pressure. Early access by horse-drawn carriages, followed by motor vehicles and sustained footfall over decades, led to significant soil compaction around its root system. This reduced the availability of water and nutrients essential for its health. More recently, the effects of climate change have exacerbated this stress. Prolonged periods of heat and reduced rain at critical times have been particularly damaging within the naturally free-draining sandy soils of Sherwood.</p>



<p>Over the years, Natural England has worked closely with Nottinghamshire County Council and more recently the RSPB to better understand and support the tree's condition. Scientific monitoring and interventions included root radar mapping, soil microfauna analysis, foliar sampling to understand nutrient uptake, and detailed soil and vegetation surveys. Management actions also included the removal of mulch and competing vegetation. These efforts have significantly advanced our understanding of the tree's physiology and the pressures it faced.</p>



<p>I have been fortunate to experience the Major Oak in many contexts: carrying out bat surveys at dusk as a volunteer, guiding site visits, sharing its story with colleagues and bringing my own family to stand beneath its vast canopy. These moments have reinforced not just its ecological importance, but its unique ability to inspire and connect people.</p>



<p>While this marks a sad moment, it is also an important reminder of ecological resilience and continuity. The death of the Major Oak does not mark the end of its contribution to the forest. On the contrary, it enters a new and equally significant phase. As the central trunk decays, it will create vital habitat for a range of specialised and rare species, including nationally scarce and near-threatened invertebrates such as darkling beetles and flies. Its hollowing structure will continue to provide roosting opportunities for bats, including brown long-eared bats. The processes of decay, fungal colonisation and habitat formation within the tree are integral to the biodiversity value of ancient woodland systems.</p>



<p>In this way, the Major Oak continues to give life. Its later stages support species that have declined across the wider countryside, making it as ecologically important in death as it was in life. Its story is not ending. It is evolving. The way people connect with the Major Oak may change, but its ability to inspire, educate and provide a focal point for shared memories will endure. For generations to come, it will provide a home to some of our most threatened species and remain a powerful symbol of Sherwood Forest's natural heritage and the enduring relationship between people and place.</p>
]]></content>
		
					<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/14/sherwood-forests-major-oak-an-ending-and-a-beginning/#comments" thr:count="16" />
			<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/14/sherwood-forests-major-oak-an-ending-and-a-beginning/feed/" thr:count="16" />
			<thr:total>16</thr:total>
			</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Denise Latham</name>
					</author>

		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Putting the wiggle back into the River Kemp]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/09/putting-the-wiggle-back-into-the-river-kemp/" />

		<id>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/?p=7439</id>
		<updated>2026-07-09T08:15:33Z</updated>
		<published>2026-07-09T08:15:09Z</published>
		<category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Catchment Sensitive Farming" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Ecosystem Services" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Flood Management" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Habitat" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Land Use" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Natural England" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Nature Recovery" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Nature-based solutions" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="biodiversity" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="catchment sensitive farming" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Environment Agency" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="farming" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="nature recovery" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="River Kemp" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="river restoration" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Severn Rivers Trust" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Shropshire" />
		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Denise Latham, Senior Officer, Catchment Sensitive Farming, Natural England What happens when a routine farm visit grows into something far more ambitious? Senior Officer Denise Latham shares the story of the Walcot Wiggle, how a conversation on a Shropshire …]]></summary>

					<content type="html" xml:base="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/09/putting-the-wiggle-back-into-the-river-kemp/"><![CDATA[
<p><strong>By Denise Latham, Senior Officer, Catchment Sensitive Farming, Natural England</strong></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p>What happens when a routine farm visit grows into something far more ambitious? Senior Officer Denise Latham shares the story of the Walcot Wiggle, how a conversation on a Shropshire hillside evolved into a landmark river restoration project that is putting the natural meanders back into the River Kemp. From funding breakthroughs to the moment water first flowed through newly restored channels, this is a story about what becomes possible when farmers, advisers and partners share a vision, and the confidence to pursue it.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p>Eighteen months ago, I visited a farm in the Clun catchment to talk through a Catchment Sensitive Farming Capital Grant application. The plan was fairly straightforward: a few ponds, some practical improvements and advice on how to make the most of the opportunities available.</p>



<p>But as I walked the farm with one of the landowners, and Helen Oliver from the Shropshire Hills National Landscape's Farming in Protected Landscapes team, it became clear there was an opportunity to think much bigger.</p>



<p>Working closely with the landowners, we brought together the right partners, including the Environment Agency and Severn Rivers Trust. Together, we explored what was possible and shaped a shared vision for restoring the river. Through those conversations and partnerships, the idea gradually grew into what became the ‘Walcot Wiggle’.</p>



<p>Projects like this do not happen without funding. The initial feasibility study was funded through a FiPL grant. The Walcot Wiggle has been supported by the Environment Agency's Local Water Environment Grant, the Shropshire Hills National Landscape 30by30 Fund, the Elgol Fund for Nature and the HDH Wills 1965 Charitable Trust.  </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="349" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Walcott-wiggle-drone-shot-before-works-completed-Credit-Severn-Rivers-Trust-620x349.png" alt="Walcott wiggle drone shot before works completed Credit Severn Rivers Trust" class="wp-image-7445" style="width:630px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Walcott-wiggle-drone-shot-before-works-completed-Credit-Severn-Rivers-Trust-620x349.png 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Walcott-wiggle-drone-shot-before-works-completed-Credit-Severn-Rivers-Trust-310x174.png 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Walcott-wiggle-drone-shot-before-works-completed-Credit-Severn-Rivers-Trust-1536x864.png 1536w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Walcott-wiggle-drone-shot-before-works-completed-Credit-Severn-Rivers-Trust.png 1600w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Walcott wiggle drone shot before works completed Credit Severn Rivers Trust</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>What we're doing and why it matters</strong></p>



<p>This section of the River Kemp was straightened in the 1800s to improve farming but, in doing so, it reduced the variety of habitats the river could support and changed the way water moved through the landscape.</p>



<p>By restoring more than a kilometre of meanders and reconnecting the river to its original channel, we are giving the River Kemp the space to behave more as it once did. That brings benefits for both people and wildlife. The "wiggles" lengthen the river's course and slow the movement of water, helping to reduce flood risk downstream. They also give sediment and nutrients more opportunity to settle, improving water quality. </p>



<p>The restored floodplain makes the landscape more resilient to a changing climate, helping it cope with both heavier rainfall and longer dry spells. At the same time, the meanders, backwaters, wetlands and seasonally wet grassland create a much richer variety of habitats for birds, fish, amphibians, insects and aquatic plants.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="778" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Digger-about-to-break-through-bund-and-reconnect-620x778.jpeg" alt="Digger about to break through bund and reconnect river" class="wp-image-7442" style="width:630px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Digger-about-to-break-through-bund-and-reconnect-620x778.jpeg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Digger-about-to-break-through-bund-and-reconnect-310x389.jpeg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Digger-about-to-break-through-bund-and-reconnect-1225x1536.jpeg 1225w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Digger-about-to-break-through-bund-and-reconnect-1633x2048.jpeg 1633w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Digger-about-to-break-through-bund-and-reconnect.jpeg 1911w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Digger about to break through a bund and reconnect the river</figcaption></figure>



<p>Because the River Kemp feeds into the River Clun, home to internationally important species including Atlantic salmon and the endangered freshwater pearl mussel, improving this stretch of river will also benefit wildlife across the wider catchment by creating cleaner water and better spawning and feeding habitats.</p>



<p>People have been shaping the River Kemp for centuries. The difference now is that we are working with the river, giving it the space to do what it does naturally and creating a more resilient landscape for farming, wildlife and the people who depend on both.</p>



<p><strong>Farming and nature, hand in hand</strong></p>



<p>One of the things I'm most proud of about the Walcot Wiggle is that it shows what's possible when farmers are given the confidence and support to work with nature.</p>



<p>Since the restoration began, Natural England CSF Advisers have been working closely with both landowners and have helped secure two Countryside Stewardship Higher Tier agreements. Although there was no certainty that the Higher Tier agreements would be available when we started, we planned the project with that in mind. The baseline surveys, design work and restoration were all carried out so that, if the opportunity came, the farmers would be well placed to secure agreements that recognised the value of making room for the river to move.</p>



<p>For me, that's one of the biggest successes of the project. We've restored the river, but we've also helped create a long term plan that supports productive farming while giving the river the space to move naturally, improving water quality, reducing flood risk and creating more room for wildlife to thrive.</p>



<p>Healthy floodplains provide multiple benefits to farming. Improved soil moisture during dry periods, more resilient grassland, reduced erosion and better water management all contribute towards productive farm businesses that are better equipped to adapt to a changing climate.</p>



<p>At the same time, wildlife benefits from a more connected landscape where rivers, wetlands and grasslands can function as a more joined up landscape.</p>



<p>For me, this is a great example of Natural England’s approach in action, putting farmers and landowners at the heart of nature recovery through practical support and local knowledge.</p>



<p><strong>The reconnection</strong></p>



<p>Standing beside the River Kemp as water flowed through its new meanders for the first time was a proud and memorable moment.</p>



<p>After 18 months of planning, surveys, discussions and collaborative working, it was incredibly rewarding to see the vision become reality. Watching the river begin to reconnect with its original channel was a reminder that river restoration is not simply about moving earth or reshaping channels; it is about restoring natural processes that will continue to evolve long after the machinery has left.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="713" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Tree-lined-channel-before-water-enters-620x713.jpeg" alt="Tree-lined channel before water enters" class="wp-image-7443" style="width:630px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Tree-lined-channel-before-water-enters-620x713.jpeg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Tree-lined-channel-before-water-enters-310x357.jpeg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Tree-lined-channel-before-water-enters-1335x1536.jpeg 1335w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Tree-lined-channel-before-water-enters-1780x2048.jpeg 1780w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Tree-lined channel before water enters</figcaption></figure>



<p>Perhaps most exciting is that this is only the beginning. As vegetation establishes, wetlands develop and wildlife responds, the benefits of the project will continue to grow year after year. We have secured long-term monitoring, allowing us to track how the site develops over time, measure the project's environmental benefits, and use this evidence to inform future restoration work. Equally importantly, the relationships built throughout the project continue to strengthen, providing opportunities to develop the site further and inspire similar projects across the Severn River Basin.</p>



<p>The Walcot Wiggle shows what can be achieved when ambitious landowners, trusted advice, sound evidence and strong partnerships come together with a shared vision. By putting the wiggle back into the River Kemp, we are helping to create a healthier river, a more resilient farming landscape and a better future for nature. I hope it provides a model that gives us, as well as other farmers and landowners, the confidence to take on similar projects.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="349" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Walcott-wiggle-after-works-completed-Credit-Severn-Rivers-Trust-620x349.jpeg" alt="Walcott wiggle after works completed. Credit: Severn Rivers Trust" class="wp-image-7444" style="width:630px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Walcott-wiggle-after-works-completed-Credit-Severn-Rivers-Trust-620x349.jpeg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Walcott-wiggle-after-works-completed-Credit-Severn-Rivers-Trust-310x174.jpeg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Walcott-wiggle-after-works-completed-Credit-Severn-Rivers-Trust-1536x864.jpeg 1536w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Walcott-wiggle-after-works-completed-Credit-Severn-Rivers-Trust-2048x1152.jpeg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Walcott wiggle after works completed. Credit: Severn Rivers Trust</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Find out more</strong> To learn more about Catchment Sensitive Farming and how we can support farmers and landowners, visit <a href="https://www.gov.uk/guidance/catchment-sensitive-farming-reduce-agricultural-water-pollution">Catchment Sensitive Farming: advice for farmers and land managers - GOV.UK</a> and <a href="https://www.farmingadviceservice.org.uk/csf">Catchment Sensitive Farming - Our advice | Farming Advice Service</a></p>
]]></content>
		
					<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/09/putting-the-wiggle-back-into-the-river-kemp/#comments" thr:count="0" />
			<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/09/putting-the-wiggle-back-into-the-river-kemp/feed/" thr:count="0" />
			<thr:total>0</thr:total>
			</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Emma Johnson</name>
					</author>

		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Assessing the Health of the River Wye Catchment: An Update]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/07/assessing-the-health-of-the-river-wye-catchment-an-update/" />

		<id>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/?p=7424</id>
		<updated>2026-07-07T11:01:12Z</updated>
		<published>2026-07-07T11:00:48Z</published>
		<category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Biodiversity" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Evidence" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Favourable Conservation Status" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Monitoring" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Natural England" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Nature Recovery" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Protected sites and species" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Site of Special Scientific Interest" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="biodiversity" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Condition assessment" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Land management" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="nature recovery" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="River" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="River Lugg" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="River Wye" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Special Area of Conservation" />
		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Emma Johnson, Midlands Deputy Director, Natural England Natural England has completed a detailed condition assessment of the River Lugg SSSI, part of the nationally protected River Wye catchment. This blog sets out the findings of that assessment, explaining the …]]></summary>

					<content type="html" xml:base="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/07/assessing-the-health-of-the-river-wye-catchment-an-update/"><![CDATA[
<p><strong>By Emma Johnson, Midlands Deputy Director, Natural England</strong></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><em>Natural England has completed a detailed condition assessment of the River Lugg SSSI, part of the nationally protected River Wye catchment. This blog sets out the findings of that assessment, explaining the key environmental pressures, including excess nutrients, fine sediment and invasive species, that are contributing to the river's "unfavourable-declining" status. It also outlines why healthy rivers matter, how climate change is likely to intensify existing challenges, and what coordinated action across the catchment can do to help restore the River Lugg to a healthier, more resilient state.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p>The River Wye and River Lugg are nationally important waterways, protected as a Site of Special Scientific Interest (SSSI) and part of a Special Area of Conservation (SAC).</p>



<p>In 2023, we published an interim assessment highlighting concerns about the condition of the River Wye and its catchment. At that time, both the Wye and the Lugg were classed as&nbsp;<strong>“unfavourable – declining”</strong>,&nbsp;with pressures from nutrients, land use and habitat change affecting key ecological features.</p>



<p>Our <a href="https://www.gov.uk/guidance/sites-of-special-scientific-interest-condition-and-assessments">guidance</a> explains the different classifications we use for SSSIs.</p>



<p>Since then, we have completed a more&nbsp;thorough&nbsp;condition assessment of the&nbsp;<strong>River Lugg SSSI,</strong> which confirms the findings of our interim assessment.</p>



<p>That’s certainly not where we want the health of our rivers to be. The new assessment provides a clearer understanding of the river’s current condition and how we can tackle the challenges ahead.</p>



<p>A full assessment of the River Wye is also underway.</p>



<p><strong>What the new assessment tells us</strong></p>



<p>The River Lugg continues to support valuable wildlife, including otters and nationally scarce invertebrates. River flows remain close to natural levels, demonstrating a degree of ecological resilience.</p>



<p>However, significant environmental challenges remain:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Phosphorus levels exceed targets throughout the Lugg catchment.</li>



<li>Fine sediment is widespread, particularly in the middle and lower river.</li>



<li>Excess nutrients are causing algal growth and changes to aquatic plant communities.</li>



<li>Invasive species such as Himalayan balsam and signal crayfish are affecting native wildlife.</li>



<li>Historic river engineering, including dredging and straightening, has reduced habitat diversity and natural river function.</li>
</ul>



<p>Taking all factors into account, the River Lugg SSSI&nbsp;is&nbsp;in <strong>“unfavourable-declining”</strong> condition.</p>



<p>While some stretches&nbsp;retain&nbsp;high ecological value, the combined impacts of nutrient enrichment, sediment, habitat&nbsp;modification&nbsp;and invasive species are limiting the river’s ability to function as a healthy, resilient system.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="226" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/The-River-Lugg-near-Leominster-has-been-historically-dredged-resulting-in-slower-flows-siltation-and-algae-cover.png" alt="The River Lugg near Leominster has been historically dredged, resulting in slower flows, siltation and algae cover." class="wp-image-7428" style="width:368px;height:auto" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The River Lugg near Leominster has been historically dredged, resulting in slower flows, siltation and algae cover.</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Why this matters</strong></p>



<p>Healthy rivers depend on a balance of clean water, natural&nbsp;flows&nbsp;and diverse habitats. When nutrients and sediment enter in excess, they can:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Drive excessive algal growth</li>



<li>Smother gravels used by fish and invertebrates</li>



<li>Reduce water clarity and plant diversity</li>



<li>Lower oxygen levels, especially in warm conditions</li>
</ul>



<p>Over time, these effects reduce&nbsp;the&nbsp;resilience&nbsp;of the&nbsp;river,&nbsp;increasing&nbsp;vulnerability to further pressures.</p>



<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="2" height="2" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/1ad90917-8df3-42a8-9e57-5048e9d466cf">Climate change is likely to intensify these challenges. Hotter, drier summers may reduce flows and increase water temperatures, while heavier rainfall can increase runoff of nutrients and sediment. These changes amplify existing pressures on the river.</p>



<p><strong>How land management can help</strong> </p>



<p>The condition of the River Lugg reflects how land has been managed over many years. Improving it will require coordinated action across the catchment, for example:&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Reducing nutrient losses from soil and manure</li>



<li>Limiting soil erosion and sediment runoff</li>



<li>Creating riverside buffer strips and planting trees</li>



<li>Reconnecting rivers with their floodplains where possible</li>



<li>Managing invasive species through catchment-wide action</li>
</ul>



<figure class="wp-block-image aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="316" height="238" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Pristine-reach-near-Aymenstry.-The-river-here-is-connected-to-its-floodplain-and-displays-classic-run-riffle-pool-habitats.png" alt="Pristine reach near Aymenstry. The river here is connected to its floodplain and displays classic “run-riffle-pool” habitats." class="wp-image-7427" style="width:413px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Pristine-reach-near-Aymenstry.-The-river-here-is-connected-to-its-floodplain-and-displays-classic-run-riffle-pool-habitats.png 316w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Pristine-reach-near-Aymenstry.-The-river-here-is-connected-to-its-floodplain-and-displays-classic-run-riffle-pool-habitats-310x233.png 310w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 316px) 100vw, 316px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Pristine reach near Aymenstry. The river here is connected to its floodplain and displays classic “run-riffle-pool” habitats.</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Working together</strong></p>



<p>Since 2023, our evidence base has strengthened,&nbsp;with input from EA and citizen science (Friends of the River&nbsp;Wye)&nbsp;giving us a clearer understanding of both the pressures affecting the River Lugg and the actions needed to address them.</p>



<p>Natural England is working with the Environment Agency, Herefordshire Council,&nbsp;Wye Catchment&nbsp;Partnership,&nbsp;the Wye and&nbsp;Usk&nbsp;Foundation, Herefordshire Wildlife&nbsp;Trust&nbsp;and other partners to tackle nutrient pollution while enabling sustainable growth. We are also working closely with our partners in Wales.</p>



<p>Many of the required actions can be supported through&nbsp;farming&nbsp;schemes&nbsp;that&nbsp;balance environmental improvements with productive land&nbsp;use.</p>



<p>The&nbsp;River Lugg&nbsp;remains&nbsp;an&nbsp;<strong>ecologically important and valuable river</strong>, but it faces complex and long-standing challenges. With sustained, coordinated effort across the catchment, we can improve its condition and help restore a healthy, resilient river system&nbsp;benefiting&nbsp;wildlife&nbsp;and people.</p>
]]></content>
		
					<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/07/assessing-the-health-of-the-river-wye-catchment-an-update/#comments" thr:count="0" />
			<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/07/assessing-the-health-of-the-river-wye-catchment-an-update/feed/" thr:count="0" />
			<thr:total>0</thr:total>
			</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Ian Marshman</name>
					</author>

		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Celebrating the Nature and Archaeology Near You]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/07/celebrating-the-nature-and-archaeology-near-you/" />

		<id>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/?p=7419</id>
		<updated>2026-07-07T07:01:24Z</updated>
		<published>2026-07-07T07:01:04Z</published>
		<category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Archaeology" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Coast and access" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Connecting People with Nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Landscape" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Landscapes and access" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="National Nature Reserve" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Natural England" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Nature Recovery" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Council for British Archaeology" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Festival of Archaeology" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Geology" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="heritage" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="landscape" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="National Nature Reserves" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="nature" />
		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Ian Marshman, Senior Officer - Historic Environment National Delivery at Natural England.&#160; In this blog,&#160;Ian Marshman reflects on An Evening With Natural England’s Archaeologists held on 24th June and looks forward to this summer’s Festival of Archaeology. This year …]]></summary>

					<content type="html" xml:base="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/07/celebrating-the-nature-and-archaeology-near-you/"><![CDATA[
<p><strong>By Ian Marshman, Senior Officer - Historic Environment National Delivery at Natural England.&nbsp;</strong></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><em>In this blog,&nbsp;Ian Marshman reflects on An Evening With Natural England’s Archaeologists held on 24<sup>th</sup> June and looks forward to this summer’s Festival of Archaeology. This year the festival is celebrating archaeology and nature from 18<sup>th</sup> July to 2<sup>nd</sup> August, </em>with walks, talks, and hands-on activities across the country.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><strong>Archaeology at Natural England</strong></p>



<p>I was excited to be part of an online Evening with Natural England’s Archaeologists on the 24<sup>th</sup> June hosted by our Chair Tony Juniper and Clemency Cooper from the Council for British Archaeology, who organised the Festival of Archaeology. This year the festival is celebrating archaeology and nature and they invited Natural England to discuss our work.</p>



<p>The cross-cutting theme was how our natural and historic environments are often inseparable, with staff across Natural England engaging with archaeology every day as we work to recover nature for growth, health and security.</p>



<p>As Tony Juniper said there is “a huge synergy that exists between the conservation and recovery of the natural environment with the efforts we need to put in to conserve and enhance the historic environment.”</p>



<p>It isn’t just our handful of historic environment specialists like me, but people right across the organisation. From our advisors working with farmers to restore habitats and protect rural heritage, to the staff and volunteers caring for National Nature Reserves (NNRs), we are all working in places that have been shaped by the interaction of people and nature over centuries.</p>



<p>Natural England’s mission is building partnership for nature’s recovery, and this includes archaeologists and heritage professionals. We work closely with partners at Historic England, local authorities and national parks who run the 80+ local Historic Environment Records across England.</p>



<p>An example of this is our new publication on <a href="https://publications.naturalengland.org.uk/publication/6365719972020224">Managing Registered Battlefields</a>, which was launched at the event. We developed this jointly with partners at Historic England, Forestry Commission and the Battlefields Trust to show how these special places can deliver more for people, nature and heritage. It’s a supplement to our existing <a href="https://historicengland.org.uk/content/docs/advice/nature-recovery-historic-environment/">Nature Recovery and the Historic Environment</a> guide.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="An Evening With Natural England&#039;s Archaeologists" width="620" height="349" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Ew1VgxMZkM4?wmode=transparent&amp;rel=0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>If you go into the woods today…</strong></p>



<p>The launch of the Festival of Archaeology will be at Westonbirt, the National Arboretum on Saturday 18<sup>th</sup> July. With Forestry England kindly providing free entry for the day. There will be walks, talks, workshops and demonstrations of bronze casting, coppicing and charcoal making. Natural England and the Countryside Code will be there too with archaeology and nature crafts.</p>



<p>Natural England and our partners will be leading guided walks and activities throughout the Festival to help you connect with the nature and archaeology near you. I have chosen some highlights below.</p>



<p>There is a rare chance to visit Ravensburgh Castle, the largest hill fort in the Chilterns, hidden beneath trees near Hexton. Join our tour to find out more about the site’s history and its future as part of Natural England’s vision for landscape-scale nature recovery in the North Chilterns.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="394" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Wooded-Bronze-Age-barrow-at-the-entrance-to-Ravensburgh-Castle-hillfort-at-Hexton-in-the-North-Chilterns.-Credit-Ian-Marshman-620x394.jpg" alt="Wooded Bronze Age barrow at the entrance to Ravensburgh Castle hillfort at Hexton in the North Chilterns. Credit: Ian Marshman." class="wp-image-7432" style="width:630px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Wooded-Bronze-Age-barrow-at-the-entrance-to-Ravensburgh-Castle-hillfort-at-Hexton-in-the-North-Chilterns.-Credit-Ian-Marshman-620x394.jpg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Wooded-Bronze-Age-barrow-at-the-entrance-to-Ravensburgh-Castle-hillfort-at-Hexton-in-the-North-Chilterns.-Credit-Ian-Marshman-310x197.jpg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Wooded-Bronze-Age-barrow-at-the-entrance-to-Ravensburgh-Castle-hillfort-at-Hexton-in-the-North-Chilterns.-Credit-Ian-Marshman.jpg 1343w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Wooded Bronze Age barrow at the entrance to Ravensburgh Castle hillfort at Hexton in the North Chilterns. Credit: Ian Marshman.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Forestry England will be leading a walk exploring if the trees of Sherwood Forest NNR could talk, in this most legendary of ancient woodlands.</p>



<p>Partners at the South West Heritage Trust are expecting a Viking Invasion with reenactors at the Avalon Marshes Centre in the Somerset Wetlands NNR.</p>



<p><strong>Adventures on the King Charles III Coast Path &amp; the Kings Series of NNRs</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="827" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Exploring-the-Dunes-of-the-North-Walney-NNR.-Ros-Campbell-620x827.jpg" alt="Exploring the Dunes of the North Walney NNR. Credit: Ros Campbell." class="wp-image-7430" style="aspect-ratio:0.7497687801870312;width:303px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Exploring-the-Dunes-of-the-North-Walney-NNR.-Ros-Campbell-620x827.jpg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Exploring-the-Dunes-of-the-North-Walney-NNR.-Ros-Campbell-310x413.jpg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Exploring-the-Dunes-of-the-North-Walney-NNR.-Ros-Campbell.jpg 1034w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Exploring the Dunes of the North Walney NNR. Credit: Ros Campbell.</figcaption></figure>



<p>At North Walney NNR near Barrow-in-Furness we’ll be leading a walk to celebrate the island’s nature and history, and how it has been shaped by the Vikings, rabbit warrens and the military.</p>



<p>NNR staff at the Ribble Estuary in Merseyside will be leading a walk along the coast path, birdwatching on the way, to visit the place where a German aircraft was shot down during World War II.&nbsp;</p>



<p>You can also join us for a journey through time into the Bradford Pennine Gateway NNR, which was declared last year as part of the King’s Series of NNRs, created to celebrate the Coronation of King Charles III. From its gritstone geology, to prehistoric rock art, the birth of the Industrial Revolution and modern history have all left their trace. There will also be family-friendly activities at Bracken Hall Countryside Centre.</p>



<p>Partners at Bradgate Park NNR near Leicester, which is also part of the King’s Series, are holding a Family Fun Day. With archaeology activities including a dig pit, spear throwing, and real Stone Age tools inspired by the site’s rare Ice Age camp, which was recorded as part of the park’s Countryside Stewardship agreement.</p>



<p>There’s another link to His Majesty King Charles III, as he is Patron of the Council for British Archaeology, and it’s a little-known fact that the King studied archaeology as a student.</p>



<p><strong>Next door nature and archaeology</strong></p>



<p>In Manchester we’ll be leading a walk through popular and lesser-known greenspaces in the city centre, on the&nbsp;hunt for urban archaeology and wildlife, with the help of partners at the National Trust and Landsec.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="349" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Mayfield-Park-in-Manchester-which-was-created-by-reusing-Victorian-structures-and-materials-from-the-sites-history.-Sarah-Cattell-620x349.jpg" alt="Mayfield Park in Manchester which was created by reusing Victorian structures and materials from the site’s history. Credit: Sarah Cattell." class="wp-image-7431" style="width:630px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Mayfield-Park-in-Manchester-which-was-created-by-reusing-Victorian-structures-and-materials-from-the-sites-history.-Sarah-Cattell-620x349.jpg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Mayfield-Park-in-Manchester-which-was-created-by-reusing-Victorian-structures-and-materials-from-the-sites-history.-Sarah-Cattell-310x174.jpg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Mayfield-Park-in-Manchester-which-was-created-by-reusing-Victorian-structures-and-materials-from-the-sites-history.-Sarah-Cattell.jpg 1379w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mayfield Park in Manchester which was created by reusing Victorian structures and materials from the site’s history. Credit: Sarah Cattell.</figcaption></figure>



<p>At Barnack Hills &amp; Holes NNR near Peterborough we’ll be exploring the geology, archaeology and nature of this unique undulating landscape, which was produced by quarrying to create medieval marvels like Peterborough and Ely Cathedrals.</p>



<p>In Sutton Coldfield in the West Midlands partners are leading both a talk and a walk at Sutton Park NNR, looking at how its woodland, heathland and grassland has been shaped by thousands of years of human activity.</p>



<p><em>For full details of these events and more visit the </em><a href="https://www.archaeologyuk.org/festival.html"><em>Festival of Archaeology website</em></a><em>. Please note pre-booking is required for some events.</em></p>



<p><em>You can also find a selection of online </em><a href="https://www.archaeologyuk.org/festival/festival-resources.html"><em>Festival Resources</em></a><em> </em><em>to try at home. This includes printable crafts, videos, and the Peat the Lapwing Game where players can restore a bog encountering archaeology and wildlife on the way.</em></p>



<p></p>
]]></content>
		
					<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/07/celebrating-the-nature-and-archaeology-near-you/#comments" thr:count="0" />
			<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/07/celebrating-the-nature-and-archaeology-near-you/feed/" thr:count="0" />
			<thr:total>0</thr:total>
			</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Kim Owen</name>
					</author>

		<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Paludiculture and Wetter Farming Fund – strengthening the case for farming on wetter peat soils]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/06/the-paludiculture-and-wetter-farming-fund-strengthening-the-case-for-farming-on-wetter-peat-soils/" />

		<id>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/?p=7402</id>
		<updated>2026-07-06T08:31:11Z</updated>
		<published>2026-07-06T08:24:50Z</published>
		<category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Climate change" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Environmental Improvement Plan" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Farming" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Food" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Land Use" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Peat" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="biodiversity" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Carbon storage" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="climate change" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Fund" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Lowland Peat" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Natural England" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="net zero" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Paludiculture" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Paludiculture and Wetter Farming" />
		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[Kim Owen and Steph Britton - Climate change, Environmental Improvement Plan, Farming, Food, Land use, Land Use Framework, Peat, Water Lowland Peat soils are vital to England’s food system, producing roughly 40% of all domestically grown vegetables, yet drainage-based agriculture …]]></summary>

					<content type="html" xml:base="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/06/the-paludiculture-and-wetter-farming-fund-strengthening-the-case-for-farming-on-wetter-peat-soils/"><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Kim Owen and Steph Britton</strong> <strong>- Climate change, Environmental Improvement Plan, Farming, Food, Land use, Land Use Framework, Peat, Water</strong></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p>Lowland Peat soils are vital to England’s food system, producing roughly 40% of all domestically grown vegetables<em>,</em> yet drainage-based agriculture is causing them to degrade at an alarming rate - releasing carbon, accelerating land subsidence, and driving biodiversity loss. On 26 June 2026, Natural England launched the Paludiculture and Wetter Farming Fund (PWFF), backed by up to £10 million from Defra, to help change that.</p>



<p>This blog explains what the fund is, how it builds on earlier research, and what it offers for farmers, nature and our climate - from growing innovative wet-adapted crops to testing whether conventional food production can work at higher water tables. Whether you're a farmer, researcher, or organisation with an interest in lowland peat, read on to find out how PWFF could work for you, and how to get involved before the application window closes on 21 August 2026.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p>The Paludiculture and Wetter Farming Fund (<strong>PWFF</strong>) launched on Friday 26<sup>th</sup> June 2026. Delivered by Natural England (NE), up to <strong>£10 million </strong>in research &amp; development funding has been made available by Defra, to encourage more responsible land use on peat soils by removing existing barriers to keeping peat wet, whilst supporting food production and water security and helping reduce the impact of climate change.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="414" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Great-Fen-Trial-Phragmites-Common-Reed.-credit-Jim-Milner-620x414.jpg" alt="Great Fen Trial - Phragmites (Common Reed). credit Jim Milner" class="wp-image-7404" style="width:630px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Great-Fen-Trial-Phragmites-Common-Reed.-credit-Jim-Milner-620x414.jpg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Great-Fen-Trial-Phragmites-Common-Reed.-credit-Jim-Milner-310x207.jpg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Great-Fen-Trial-Phragmites-Common-Reed.-credit-Jim-Milner.jpg 1057w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Great Fen Trial - Phragmites (Common Reed). credit Jim Milner</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>What is Paludiculture and Wetter Farming?</strong></p>



<p>Based on the findings from the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/new-investment-in-peat-in-fight-against-climate-change">Paludiculture Exploration Fund</a> which supported early research and trials, (for example, developing crops into products such as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.paludiculture.org.uk/fibrebroads">construction materials in the Broads; using Typha seed heads to replace polyester in clothing insulation); </a>PWFF now takes a more focused approach:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Paludiculture </strong>is the growing of crops adapted to wet conditions (with a grant focus on <em>Phragmites </em>(reed), <em>Typha</em> (bulrush), <em>Sphagnum</em> (moss)) to produce a variety of products. For example, horticultural peat replacement, acoustic panels.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Wetter farming&nbsp;</strong>is&nbsp;the&nbsp;practice of growing&nbsp;conventional&nbsp;<strong>food</strong> crops (typically those cultivated on drained peat (or other soils)) at higher water tables.</li>
</ul>



<p>PWFF will fund projects to develop markets and test systems at scale across these two priority themes.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="620" height="828" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Beadamoss-Sphagnum-paludiculture-plots-credit-Jim-Milner-620x828.jpg" alt="Beadamoss Sphagnum paludiculture plots. Credit: Jim Milner" class="wp-image-7406" style="width:630px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Beadamoss-Sphagnum-paludiculture-plots-credit-Jim-Milner-620x828.jpg 620w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Beadamoss-Sphagnum-paludiculture-plots-credit-Jim-Milner-310x414.jpg 310w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Beadamoss-Sphagnum-paludiculture-plots-credit-Jim-Milner.jpg 651w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 620px) 100vw, 620px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Beadamoss Sphagnum paludiculture plots. Credit: Jim Milner</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Natural England’s ‘Strategy in Action’</strong></p>



<p>PWFF is a great example of Natural England’s <strong>‘Strategy in Action</strong>’. The rewetting of lowland peat for crop production has the potential to sustain livelihoods, support food security, water resilience, nature recovery, net zero (through carbon sequestration/reduction of carbon loss from degraded peat) and manage climate risks such as flooding and drought. As a result, PWFF contributes to stronger, more resilient ecosystems, supporting economic growth, public health and national security.</p>



<p><strong>Contributing to Net Zero</strong></p>



<p>PWFF is part of the government’s approach to achieving Net Zero by moving away from drainage-based agriculture in lowland peatlands in England. When peat is drained, the carbon stored in the peat is released into the atmosphere, primarily as carbon dioxide. A further carbon cost is added when energy is used to pump water from the peat. Peat drainage also accelerates peat soil erosion, land subsidence and biodiversity loss.&nbsp;</p>



<p>PWFF will provide rewetting opportunities, potentially enabling farmers to achieve/maintain high water tables which would slow peat degradation/loss, and could significantly reduce the greenhouse gas emissions associated with drained peat, while contributing to nature recovery.</p>



<p><strong>How can farming on wetted peat help bitterns?</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="261" height="347" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Lancashire-Wildlife-Trust-Typha-harvest-credit-Jim-Milner.jpg" alt="Lancashire Wildlife Trust, Typha harvest. Credit: Jim Milner" class="wp-image-7407" style="aspect-ratio:0.7521820538672044;width:218px;height:auto" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Lancashire Wildlife Trust, Typha harvest. Credit: Jim Milner</figcaption></figure>



<p>Developing markets for paludiculture products through PWFF will potentially provide a sustainable income stream for protected wetland site management, such as for Bitterns. For example, more lucrative markets could be created for harvested reed, from traditional uses (thatching) to new, innovative uses (insulation board).</p>



<p>It gets better…… the rewetting of peat through PWFF will help support the maintenance of higher water levels elsewhere in the lowland landscape where desired/appropriate, such as for protected wetland sites and peatlands undergoing restoration. <a href="https://www.clr.conservation.cam.ac.uk/news/birds-could-benefit-wetter-ways-farming">Research has also shown</a> that paludiculture sites contained three times more birds than agricultural grassland sites, including several threatened bird species - nature recovery in action.</p>



<p><strong>What’s in it for our farmers?</strong></p>



<p>The rewetting opportunities offered by PWFF, which are so important for reducing carbon emissions and for nature recovery, support sustainable farming systems on peat soils into the long term, particularly by reducing peat loss and land subsidence in under-pressure landscapes.</p>



<p>PWFF projects will focus on developing commercially viable products from   paludiculture crops <strong><em>Phragmites </em></strong>(reed),<strong><em>Typha </em></strong>(bulrush)and <strong><em>Sphagnum</em></strong> (moss), mainly through the development of reliable supply chains and product certification, supporting more resilient farming businesses in a changing economy and climate. &nbsp;</p>



<p>We also want to investigate how water can be managed to grow conventional <strong>food</strong> crops at higher water tables on peat. For example, by developing practical high water table growing systems; adapting machinery and improving access to suitable machinery for planting, harvesting, processing.</p>



<p>PWFF will help strengthen the commercial case for continuing farming on wetter peat soils with less damaging environmental effects.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="542" height="336" src="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Mixed-habitats-around-a-Typha-plot-credit-Steph-Britton.jpg" alt="Mixed habitats around a Typha plot. Credit: Steph Britton" class="wp-image-7408" style="width:630px;height:auto" srcset="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Mixed-habitats-around-a-Typha-plot-credit-Steph-Britton.jpg 542w, https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/183/2026/07/Mixed-habitats-around-a-Typha-plot-credit-Steph-Britton-310x192.jpg 310w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mixed habitats around a Typha plot. Credit: Steph Britton</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Collaboration is key!</strong></p>



<p>Partnerships are key to the success of PWFF projects. A consortium-building database is available, hosted by Defra’s delivery partner&nbsp;NIAB, for organisations and businesses looking to work together on potential lowland peat water projects, including PWFF (NE can be part of a consortium bid but not lead one). To find out more, you can log your details in this&nbsp;<a href="http://www.paludiculture.org.uk/consortium-building-form">consortium-building database</a>, hosted by <a href="http://www.paludiculture.org.uk">www.paludiculture.org.uk</a>.</p>



<p>The partnerships and projects developed through PWFF will help encourage a transition to a more sustainable land use on lowland peat. The vision is to create a mosaic of different land uses and management approaches, where restored peatlands, productive farming and nature rich habitats sit alongside each other. Multiple benefits will be delivered through multiple partnerships – truly NE's ‘Strategy in Action’.</p>



<p>Applications can be submitted via the <a href="https://atamis-9529.my.salesforce-sites.com/ProSpend__CS_ContractPage?SearchType=Projects&amp;uid=a07P200001zRhfgIAC&amp;searchStr=&amp;sortStr=Recently+Published&amp;page=1&amp;filters=&amp;County=">Defra eCommercial portal</a>, between <strong>26 June 2026 and 21 August 2026</strong>.</p>



<p><strong>Want to know more?</strong></p>



<p>You can find out more on the <a href="https://find-government-grants.service.gov.uk/grants/paludiculture-and-wetter-farming-fund-1">Find a Grant website</a>.</p>



<p>Natural England will host an <strong>Application Webinar on 7 July 2026</strong>. To register, and for more information on PWFF, please email <a href="mailto:PWFF@naturalengland.org.uk">PWFF@naturalengland.org.uk</a></p>
]]></content>
		
					<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/06/the-paludiculture-and-wetter-farming-fund-strengthening-the-case-for-farming-on-wetter-peat-soils/#comments" thr:count="0" />
			<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/07/06/the-paludiculture-and-wetter-farming-fund-strengthening-the-case-for-farming-on-wetter-peat-soils/feed/" thr:count="0" />
			<thr:total>0</thr:total>
			</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Natural England</name>
					</author>

		<title type="html"><![CDATA[What Natural England is doing next to protect Dartmoor Ponies]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/06/30/what-natural-england-is-doing-next-to-protect-dartmoor-ponies/" />

		<id>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/?p=7393</id>
		<updated>2026-07-02T09:02:52Z</updated>
		<published>2026-06-30T16:24:44Z</published>
		<category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Farming" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Grazing" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Natural England" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Protected sites and species" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Site of Special Scientific Interest" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="wildlife and farming" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="biodiversity" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Conservation" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Dartmoor" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Dartmoor Hill Ponies" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="grazing" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Land use" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Position" />
		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[In recent weeks, Dartmoor's iconic ponies have been at the centre of significant media attention and public debate. We want to use this blog to set out clearly what has been reported, what is happening in reality, and what we …]]></summary>

					<content type="html" xml:base="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/06/30/what-natural-england-is-doing-next-to-protect-dartmoor-ponies/"><![CDATA[
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p>In recent weeks, Dartmoor's iconic ponies have been at the centre of significant media attention and public debate. We want to use this blog to set out clearly what has been reported, what is happening in reality, and what we are doing next.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><strong>What has been reported</strong></p>



<p>We have already <a href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/06/09/dartmoor-ponies-clarification-of-natural-englands-role-and-position/">corrected false claims</a> made in media articles last week suggesting that Natural England is proposing to cull Dartmoor ponies as part of biodiversity plans for the moor. We understand why these headlines have caused distress to pony owners, to people who love Dartmoor and to communities across the South West who have a deep connection to these animals.</p>



<p>We continue to be clear that no cull of Dartmoor ponies has been proposed, approved or is being pursued by Natural England. We recognise, though, that the situation which has led to this coverage is real and complex, and deserves a more careful explanation than headlines allow.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><strong>What’s actually happening</strong></p>



<p>Dartmoor is a designated Site of Special Scientific Interest (SSSI) and one of England's most ecologically important landscapes. The moorland habitats it supports - blanket bog, heath and grassland - depend on the right kind and level of grazing, by sheep, cattle and ponies, to remain in good condition. When grazing levels are too high, sensitive plant communities are damaged. When they are too low, vegetation such as Molinia (purple moor grass) can encroach over time, reducing both biodiversity and forage for livestock.</p>



<p>Dartmoor ponies are a native breed and are an integral part of that grazing system. They have shaped the moor for centuries and Natural England absolutely values their role in it. The difficulty is that, in some areas, grazing levels are higher than the habitat can sustain in the long term. This is not a new problem and it is not one with a simple solution. This is about getting the right type of grazing, in the right place and at the right time of year. Across large, unfenced areas this has to be supported by viable farming to be sustainable.</p>



<p>Managing livestock numbers on common land is a genuinely complicated matter. It involves the rights of commoners, the economics of traditional upland farming, animal welfare obligations, and the ecological needs of protected habitats. These things can pull in different directions and any approach that ignores that complexity risks causing harm to farming livelihoods, to wildfire risk, or to the very habitats we are all trying to protect.</p>



<p>Natural England strongly believes that a viable pony population is essential for nature recovery on Dartmoor, as well as for their huge cultural and aesthetic value.</p>



<p>Balancing this with all the other interests such as sheep and cattle farming will take a strong partnership effort over the coming years – there is no quick fix.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><strong>What we are doing</strong></p>



<p>We are working with Defra on the broader policy questions this situation has raised, including whether current frameworks adequately support the kind of land management that Dartmoor needs.</p>



<p>Natural England is working closely with Defra, the Commoners’ Council, pony owners, the Dartmoor Land Use Management Group and the Dartmoor National Park on a considered, collaborative approach. We are holding a series of meetings with them in the coming weeks.&nbsp;</p>



<p>To achieve our goals of sustainable farming and nature recovery on Dartmoor will take time and require a lot of continued collaboration. There are no quick fixes. NE is committed to playing our part.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Our people on the ground</strong></p>



<p>Our Local Team includes people dedicated to working on Dartmoor and they regularly meet with commoners, pony keepers, farmers and conservation groups. They know the moor, have built relationships with those who live and work there over many years and understand that the ecology of Dartmoor and the livelihoods of the people who manage it are not separate concerns.</p>



<p>There is a genuine, shared desire among the people closest to Dartmoor to find workable solutions and we look forward to working with all parties to safeguard the future of ponies on the moor.</p>



<p><strong>Next steps</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>We will provide a further update once our upcoming stakeholder meetings have taken place. if you have questions or concerns, you can contact us at customer.feedback@naturalengland.org.uk</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p><strong>A note on comments</strong></p>



<p><em>We welcome comments on our blog, but please keep the conversation respectful. Comments are moderated in line with our policy.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />



<p></p>
]]></content>
		
					<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/06/30/what-natural-england-is-doing-next-to-protect-dartmoor-ponies/#comments" thr:count="19" />
			<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/06/30/what-natural-england-is-doing-next-to-protect-dartmoor-ponies/feed/" thr:count="19" />
			<thr:total>19</thr:total>
			</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>Natural England</name>
					</author>

		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Natural England response to Badger Trust and Wild Justice judicial review decision]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/06/29/natural-england-response-to-badger-trust-and-wild-justice-judicial-review-decision-2/" />

		<id>https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/?p=7389</id>
		<updated>2026-06-29T11:14:12Z</updated>
		<published>2026-06-29T11:00:17Z</published>
		<category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Natural England" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Nature" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Badger" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Badger Trust" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Court" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Judicial review" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Statement" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="Wild Justice" /><category scheme="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk" term="wildlife" />
		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[The High Court has on 26 June 2026, dismissed the judicial review claim brought by Wild Justice and the Badger Trust, finding no unlawfulness in Natural England’s decision-making.  The Court declined to grant the declaration sought by the claimants, noting …]]></summary>

					<content type="html" xml:base="https://naturalengland.blog.gov.uk/2026/06/29/natural-england-response-to-badger-trust-and-wild-justice-judicial-review-decision-2/"><![CDATA[
<p>The High Court has on 26 June 2026, dismissed the judicial review claim brought by Wild Justice and the Badger Trust, finding no unlawfulness in Natural England’s decision-making.  The Court declined to grant the declaration sought by the claimants, noting that the issues raised were hypothetical in nature. The Court also made no order as to costs.</p>



<p>Natural England welcomes the clarity provided by the Court.  </p>



<p></p>
]]></content>
		
			</entry>
	</feed>
